Wilhelm Fliess Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Wilhelm Fliess Papers 1894-1929
MSS84880
Fliess, Wilhelm, 1858-1928
70 items
1 container
.4 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Physician. Correspondence, writings, a reminiscence, and clippings chiefly concerning a plagiarism controversy involving Fliess, Sigmund Freud, Hermann Swoboda, and Otto Weininger. Also featured are letters from Josef Breuer to Fliess, a letter from Oscar Rie, and an undated reminiscence written by Fliess’s son, Conrad Fliess.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Breuer, Josef, 1842-1925--Correspondence.; Fliess, Conrad. Conrad Fliess reminiscences. undated.; Fliess, Wilhelm, 1858-1928.; Freud, Sigmund, 1856-1939.; Rie, Oscar, 1863-1931--Correspondence.; Swoboda, Hermann, 1873-1962.; Weininger, Otto, 1880-1903.
Subjects
Bisexuality.; Plagiarism.
Occupations
Physicians.
Provenance
The papers of Wilhelm Fliess were given to the Library of Congress by Anna Freud in 1970. Additional items were given by the Sigmund Freud Archives between 1964 and 1987.
Related Material
Sigmund Freud’s letters to Fliess (1887-1904), an important source on the formative years of psychoanalysis, are located in the Sigmund Freud Papers in the Manuscript Division of the Library of Congress.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Wilhelm Fliess are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Wilhelm Fliess (1858-1928) span the years 1894-1929 and include correspondence, writings, a reminiscence, and clippings, all of which are in German. A large portion of the papers concerns a plagiarism controversy surrounding the publication of Otto Weininger’s Geschlect und Charakter in 1903. Weininger’s book contained theories on bisexuality similar to those developed by Fliess. Fliess alleged that Sigmund Freud had discussed his theories with Hermann Swoboda who then related them to Weininger. Included is a draft and published text of Fliess’s pamphlet on the subject, In Eigener Sache. Accompanying the pamphlet are letters to and from Fliess and a clipping file concerning Fliess’s allegations.
Also featured in the papers are letters dated 1894-1898 from Joseph Breuer, a letter from Oscar Rie dated 1895, an undated draft of a writing by Fliess entitled “Die Entdeckung der Dauernden Doppelgeschlechtigkeit: Eine geschichtliche Darstellung,” and reminiscences by Fliess’s son, Conrad Fliess, contained in a letter to Richard Pfennig.
Container List
- General correspondence (Box 1)
  - From (Box 1)
    - Breuer, Josef, 1894-1898 (Box 1)
    - Rie, Oscar, 1895 (Box 1)
  - To miscellaneous, 1894, 1925 (Box 1)
- Miscellany, 1902, undated (Box 1)
- Reminiscences by Conrad Fliess (son), undated (Box 1)
- Writings (Box 1)
  - “Die Entdeckung der dauernden Doppelgeschlechtigkeit: Eine geschichtliche Darstellung,” undated (Box 1)
  - In Eigener Sache (Box 1)
    - Drafts, circa 1906, (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Published text, 1906 (Box 1)
    - Related material (Box 1)
      - Clippings, 1906-1910, undated (Box 1)
      - Correspondence, 1906-1907, 1913-1929, (2 folders) (Box 1)